<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Excellency of monarchy a panegyrick written anno 1658 / by a learned and truly loyal gentleman for information of the miserably misled Commonwealths-men (falsly so called) of that deceitful age and now reviv'd by a friend to the author and an honourer of the establish'd government of these nations.</title>
            <author>Learned and truly loyal gentleman.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39002</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34909</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14907239</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14907239</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102847</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39002)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102847)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1569:47)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Excellency of monarchy a panegyrick written anno 1658 / by a learned and truly loyal gentleman for information of the miserably misled Commonwealths-men (falsly so called) of that deceitful age and now reviv'd by a friend to the author and an honourer of the establish'd government of these nations.</title>
                  <author>Learned and truly loyal gentleman.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 broadside.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:102847:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <head>THE Excellency of MONARCHY: A PANEGYRICK, Written <hi>Anno</hi> 1658. by a <hi>Learned</hi> and truly <hi>Loyal</hi> Gentleman, for <hi>Information</hi> of the miſerably miſled <hi>Commonwealths-men</hi> (falſly ſo called) of that <hi>deceitful Age;</hi> and <hi>now reviv'd</hi> by <hi>a Friend</hi> to the <hi>Author,</hi> and an <hi>Honourer</hi> of the <hi>Eſtabliſh'd Government</hi> of theſe <hi>Nations.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg n="1">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>IF wanting <hi>wings</hi> one may aſcend the <hi>Skies,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Phaebus</hi> view, without an <hi>Eagles</hi> Eyes,</l>
               <l>Then Rouze up <hi>(Muſe)</hi> from thy <hi>Lethargick ſtrains,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And (having firſt <hi>invok'd</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of Brains)</l>
               <l>Let the grand <hi>Subject</hi> of thy <hi>Meaſures</hi> be,</l>
               <l>No <hi>Rule</hi> to <hi>England</hi> like a <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="2">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>It is the <hi>Image</hi> of that <hi>Domination,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By which <hi>Jehova</hi> rules the whole <hi>Creation:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Angels</hi> nor <hi>Saints,</hi> do in <hi>his Kingdom</hi> ſhare,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Sole Monarch, They</hi> but <hi>Subjects</hi> are:</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>Laws</hi> are <hi>ſuch,</hi> as when they did <hi>Rebell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sequeſter'd</hi> not, but ſent <hi>them</hi> ſtrait to <hi>Hell.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="3">
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>As <hi>Old</hi> as that <hi>Paternal Soveraignty</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God</hi> plac'd in <hi>Adam,</hi> rul'd his <hi>People</hi> by;</l>
               <l>Diſown'd by <hi>None,</hi> but them whoſe <hi>Minds</hi> aſpire,</l>
               <l>And envy <hi>ONE</hi> ſhould have what <hi>ALL</hi> deſire:</l>
               <l>For, be't a <hi>Few,</hi> or <hi>Many</hi> we live under,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such</hi> ſhall <hi>repine,</hi> ſtill, whilſt not of the <hi>Number.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="4">
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Antients</hi> did a <hi>Monarchy</hi> prefer,</l>
               <l>Made all their <hi>Gods</hi> ſubmit to <hi>Jupiter:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And (when <hi>Affairs</hi> and <hi>Nations</hi> firſt began)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Princes Decrees</hi> were th'only <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>Man;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Experience</hi> will avow it, where there's <hi>Any,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>One Honeſt Man</hi> is ſooner found, than <hi>Many.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="5">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>The <hi>Rational Soul</hi> performs a <hi>Prince</hi>'s part,</l>
               <l>She <hi>rules</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> by <hi>Monarchick</hi> Art;</l>
               <l>Poor <hi>Cranes,</hi> and little <hi>Bees</hi> (with ſhiv'ring wings)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Obſerve</hi> their <hi>Leaders,</hi> and <hi>Obey</hi> their <hi>Kings:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nature</hi> her ſelf, diſdains a <hi>Crowded Throne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Body</hi>'s <hi>Monſtrous,</hi> has more <hi>Heads</hi> than <hi>One.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="6">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Monarchy</hi>'s that <hi>Politick ſimple State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Conſiſts in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> (inſeparate,</l>
               <l>Pure and entire) a <hi>Government</hi> that <hi>ſtands,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>When others <hi>fall,</hi> touch'd but with <hi>Levelling hands:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>Natural,</hi> and with ſuch <hi>Skill</hi> endu'd,</l>
               <l>It makes <hi>One Body</hi> of a <hi>Multitude.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="7">
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>In <hi>Order</hi> (wherein <hi>later things</hi> depend,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>former</hi>) that's moſt <hi>perfect</hi> doth attend</l>
               <l>On <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity:</hi> But this can never be</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pop'lar State,</hi> nor <hi>Aristocracy;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For where or <hi>All,</hi> or <hi>Many</hi> bear the ſway,</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Order</hi> to <hi>Confuſion</hi> leads the way.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="8">
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Monarchy</hi> more quickly doth attain</l>
               <l>The <hi>End propos'd;</hi> For 'tis the <hi>ſingle Brain</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>ripens Councel,</hi> and concealeth beſt</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Princely Deſigns,</hi> 'tis <hi>Deeds</hi> proclaim 'em <hi>Bleſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whilſt <hi>numerous Heads</hi> are rarely of <hi>one Mind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Slow</hi> in their <hi>Motion, louder</hi> than the <hi>Wind.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="9">
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Treaſon,</hi> nor <hi>Fear,</hi> ſo ſuddenly <hi>divides</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Th' <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Strength</hi> that in a <hi>Crown</hi> reſides;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sedition</hi> proſpers not, it ſeldom <hi>here</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reſults the <hi>Object</hi> of a <hi>Prince's Fear:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then when an <hi>Empire, Rome</hi> was ne're ſo <hi>ſtrong,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor <hi>Triumph'd</hi> under other <hi>Rule</hi> ſo <hi>long.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="10">
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>A <hi>Monarchy</hi> abates thoſe <hi>Feveriſh Fits</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Emulation,</hi> a <hi>Free-State</hi> begets;</l>
               <l>A <hi>Prince</hi> cannot his <hi>Reins</hi> ſo quickly <hi>ſlack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Or <hi>throw</hi> his <hi>Burthen</hi> on Another's <hi>Back:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But where ſo <hi>many Rulers</hi> have <hi>Command,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>Work's transferr'd,</hi> and <hi>toſs'd</hi> from <hi>hand</hi> to <hi>hand.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="11">
               <head>11.</head>
               <l>The <hi>People,</hi> or the <hi>Nobles,</hi> to debate</l>
               <l>The <hi>deep Concernments</hi> of a <hi>Troubled State,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Set Times</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> have aſſign'd <hi>them, they</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>meet,</hi> and then <hi>adjourn</hi> from <hi>day</hi> to <hi>day:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whereas a <hi>Monarch,</hi> who by <hi>Nature</hi>'s <hi>One,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delib'rates always,</hi> never's <hi>off</hi> his <hi>Throne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg n="12">
               <head>12.</head>
               <l>But hold! methinks I <hi>ſee</hi> the <hi>Three Eſtates</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Conven'd;</hi> Thrown open <hi>Priſon doors</hi> and <hi>Grates,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Extinct our <hi>paltry Jealouſies</hi> and <hi>Fears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grace</hi> offered to <hi>All,</hi> but <hi>Cavaliers</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Papiſts!</hi> yet with <hi>patience</hi> they abound,</l>
               <l>In <hi>hopes of better,</hi> Now, the <hi>Wheel</hi> goes <hi>Round.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Monarchia à Monos Archôn; The <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>One Prince</hi> or <hi>Governour,</hi> without a <hi>Peer,</hi> or the <hi>Government</hi> of <hi>One Man</hi> over <hi>Many,</hi> as in <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Britannia</hi> ab initio Mundi ſemper ſuit Regia, &amp; Regimen illius ſimile ille Coelorum.</q>
               <bibl>Howell's Praed. Baſil.</bibl>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
